Finding Aid for Dorothy Smith McAllister papers, ca. 1932-1967
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dorothy Smith McAllister papers circa 1932-1967
McAllister, Dorothy Smith, 1899-1983.
87150 Aa 2; mf403c; mf404c
Files relating to Democratic Party activities (largely on microfilm); files relating to her interest in civil rights, fair employment practices, and her involvement with the Michigan and National Consumers League.
2 boxes
2 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 7361 ) was donated in 1986 by McAllister's daughter, Claire McAllister White. A portion of the collection was made available for microfilming. Additional materials came in 1987 and 1988.
No further additions to the records are expected.
Restricted access on microfilm.
Dorothy Smith McAllister was born in Grand Rapids, Michigan in 1899, the daughter of a prominent local surgeon, Richard Root Smith and his wife, Myra (Raiguel Wonderly) Smith. In 1915 she graduated from the Maderia School in Greenway, Virginia. Continuing her education at Bryn Mawr College, she received her A.B. degree with honors in 1920. Thirty years later she earned her master's degree with honors in political science from the University of Michigan.
From 1928 to 1931 she held office as president of the Junior League of Grand Rapids. From there, she joined the Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform, and served as member of the board and chairman of the State Committee on Temperance Education.
From 1937 to 1941, during the second administration of President Franklin D. Roosevelt, Mrs. McAllister served as the director of the Women's Division of the Democratic National Committee. In this capacity, she gave speeches throughout the country in support of the New Deal and Roosevelt. She was also strongly involved in the Division's "Reporter Plan," a system designed to make the average citizen more aware of policies and activities of the Roosevelt Administration.
Mrs. McAllister resigned her political positions when President Roosevelt appointed her husband a federal judge. Soon thereafter, she accepted a Presidential appointment to the Volunteer Participation Committee in the 6th Army Corps Area Office of Civilian Defense. After World War II, her involvement in civic affairs was primarily on the state and local level.
McAllister was heavily involved in affairs of the state of Michigan. She served on a total of ten different state commissions, among which were civil rights, migratory labor, social security, and revision of the state constitution. She received her appointments from six different Michigan governors over a thirty-year period.
On the local level, in the early 1950s, Mrs. McAllister did a study with Helen Claytor on the need for a human relations commission in Grand Rapids. As a result, a commission was formed in 1955. Mrs. McAllister was appointed to it and served for 10 years, mainly as chairman of its housing and anti-poverty committees.
The Dorothy Smith McAllister collection consists of files relating to Democratic Party activities (largely on microfilm); files relating to her interest in civil rights, fair employment practices, and her involvement with the Michigan and National Consumers League. The collection has two parts: original manuscripts and papers that have been microfilmed. A portions of the Original Materials series also appears on the microfilm, but the microfilmed material is unique--not a part of the papers.
Subjects:
Civil rights--Michigan.; Consumers League of Michigan.; Democratic National Committee (U.S.). Women's Division.; Discrimination in employment--Michigan.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); National Consumers' League.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; McAllister, Dorothy Smith, 1899-1983.
- Original Materials
  The Original materials series comprise approximately 2 linear feet of topical files. Included are extensive files from the Michigan Commission on Status of Women and the Grand Rapids Human Relations Commission. Limited files exist on migrant labor, civil rights, consumer leagues, the Michigan Fair Employment Commission, and the Michigan European Refugees Committee. Each of these files is sketchy or limited to a brief span of time.
  Most of the material consists of minutes, bulletins, and reports of activities in which McAllister was integrally involved. Correspondence is included as well, but is by no means voluminous in quantity.
  Two small files of secondary interest include material on McAllister's husband, Thomas F. McAllister, and their daughter, Claire McAllister White.
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights
    - 1947-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1953 (Box 1)
    - Equal Rights Amendment 1950-1956 (Box 1)
    - Governor's Advisory Commission 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - Grand Rapids Chapter 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - NAACP 1952 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Consumers League of Michigan
    - Annual Report December 1953 (Box 1)
    - Bulletin 1947-1953 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1945-1956 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Democratic Party-correspondence, clipping 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Fair Employment Practices Commission
    (Michigan)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1952 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - Laws 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    - Memos, clippings, etc. 1955 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Steering Committee meeting of the Michigan Co-ordinating Council for 1955 (Box 1)
    - Tribute to D.S. McAllister June 1955 (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids Human Relations Commission
    - 1952-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1962 (Box 1)
      (Reports, Surveys)
    - 1957-1961 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1965 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Commission on Migratory Labor 1950-1957 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Commission on Status of Women
    - 1962 (Box 1)
    - 1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Constitutional Revision Commission 1942 (Box 2)
  - Michigan European Refugee Committee
    - 1956-1960 (Box 2)
  - National Consumers League
    - Anniversary Dinner December 1949 (Box 2)
    - Branch Leagues (Box 2)
    - Bulletin 1949-1955 (Box 2)
      (scattered)
    - Correspondence
      - 1948-1949 (Box 2)
      - 1950-1951 (Box 2)
      - 1952-1954 (Box 2)
      - 1955, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Financial Statements 1946-1950 (Box 2)
    - Future Program Committee 1948 (Box 2)
    - Minutes of Board of Directors meetings 1947-1957 (Box 2)
    - Statements 1947-1957 (Box 2)
  - Speeches 1967 undated (Box 2)
  - Testimonial Letters 1967 (Box 2)
  - Thomas F. McAllister
    (husband)
    - Biographical Data (Box 2)
  - Claire McAllister White
    (daughter)
    - Book of Poems 1964 (Box 2)
- Microfilm, 2 reels
  The microfilm portion of the collection consists of two reels of film, approximately one linear foot of papers. Of special note here are her files as director of the Women's Division of the Democratic National Committee from 1937 until 1941. These consist mainly of speeches (and related materials) given at various conferences across the country by McAllister. Other materials microfilmed concern her work with the Women's Division during the 1940 Presidential Campaign and her involvement with the Reporter Plan. Correspondents in the collection include Franklin Roosevelt, Eleanor Roosevelt, Frank Murphy, and Molly Dewson.
  Other files microfilmed relate to Mrs. McAllister's early career. There are numerous news clippings dating from 1932 to 1948 which deal with her government work. Also found here are small amounts of material dealing with the Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform and with Civil Defense.
  - "American Forum of the Air," Radio Interview October, 1940 (Reel 1)
  - Articles about D.S. McAllister 1939, undated (Reel 1)
  - Articles by D.S. McAllister, 194? and undated (Reel 1)
  - Civilian Defense 1941-1942 (Reel 1)
  - Clippings
    - 1932 (Reel 1)
    - 1933-1934 (Reel 1)
    - 1935 (Reel 1)
    - 1936 (Reel 1)
    - 1937 (Reel 1)
    - 1938 (Reel 1)
    - 1939 (Reel 1)
    - 1940 (Reel 1)
    - 1941-1943 undated (Reel 1)
    - 1944-1948 (Reel 1)
  - Committee for clarifying the constitution by amendment 1936-1937 (Reel 1)
  - Democratic Party, Michigan
    - Correspondence and reports 1934 (Reel 1)
    - Upper Peninsula Trip 1935 (Reel 1)
    - Convention 1940 (Reel 1)
  - Dewson, Molly, Vice-Chairman, National Democratic Committee
    - Speeches (5) undated (Reel 1)
  - Liberty League
    - Clippings and correspondence 1935 (Reel 1)
  - Minimum Wage 1935-1947 (Reel 1)
  - Precinct Organization 1939-1946 (Reel 1)
  - Presidential Campaign 1944
    - Correspondence (Reel 1)
  - Speeches
    - Women's Roosevelt Club May, 1935 (Reel 1)
    - Michigan, Radio 1936 (Reel 1)
    - "A Woman Looks at the Democratic Platform," University of VA. July, 1936 (Reel 1)
    - Young Democrats National Convention 1937 (Reel 1)
    - Women's court and Civic conference, Milwaukee September, 1937 (Reel 1)
    - Connecticut Regional Conference 1937 (Reel 1)
    - Kansas City February, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Montgomery, Alabama, Regional Conference April, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Augusta, Maine, State Convention April, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Columbia, South Carolina-Regional Conference April, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Boston August, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - WJSV Radio, Washington, D.C. September, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Michigan State Convention, Grand Rapids September, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Indianapolis, Indiana November, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Springfield, Illinois November, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - CBS November, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - American Student Union National Convention, New York City December 28, 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Chicago Regional Conference 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Introduction of Frances Perkins 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Oklahoma City Regional Conference 1938 (Reel 1)
    - Radio, Sioux Falls 1938 also Regional Conference of the Midwestern States (Reel 1)
    - Biennial Conference, Affiliated Democratic Women's Clubs March 23, 1939 (Reel 1)
    - "What's Ahead for Democratic Women," St. Louis May 5, 1939 (Reel 1)
    - Winston-Salem, North Carolina-Regional Conference May, 1939 (Reel 1)
    - New York Regional Conference June, 1939 (Reel 1)
    - Young Democrats Clubs, First Annual Convention June, 1939 (Reel 1)
    - "The Congress of Youth," New York City July, 1939 (Reel 1)
    - Institute of Government, West Virginia August, 1939 (Reel 1)
    - "Democratic Women's Day" Radio Broadcast September, 1939 (Reel 1)
    - Salt Lake City Conference October, 1939 (Reel 1)
    - "Let's talk it over"-Mrs. McAllister, Miss Marion Martin-Broadcast November, 1939 (Reel 1)
    - Democratic Women of New York State January, 1940 (Reel 1)
    - New York City State Meeting January, 1940 (Reel 1)
    - "The Fight for Democracy in 1940" Washington, D.C. March, 1940 (Reel 1)
    - Michigan Institute of Government March, 1940 (Reel 1)
    - National Institute of Government, Washington, D.C. May, 1940 (Reel 1)
    - "Do Political Parties Educate," Town Hall, New York May, 1940 (Reel 1)
    - Democratic National Convention July, 1940 (Reel 1)
    - "Social Gains and the New Deal," 1940 (Reel 1)
    - "National Defense and New Deal," 1940 (Reel 1)
    - "Serving your community in time of crisis through the Democratic Party" Wellesley College July, 1941 (Reel 1)
    - "Women and Civilian Defense," Topeka, Kansas February, 1942 (Reel 1)
    - South High School, Grand Rapids May, 1943 (Reel 1)
    - Jerseyville, Illinois 1944 (Reel 1)
    - National Democratic Convention 1944 (Reel 1)
  - Speeches (Dates uncertain)
    - "New World Unity-Our Answer to the Dictators," Washington, D.C., [ca. April, 1941] (Reel 1)
    - "Opportunities for Volunteers in the Civilian Defense Program," December, 194(?) (Reel 1)
    - Prohibition Repeal (3) circa 1931 (Reel 1)
    - Springfield, Massachusetts, February 13, ? (Reel 1)
    - Conferences for Radio, no date (Reel 1)
    - Radio, no date (Reel 1)
    - "Women's Role in National Defense," Milwaukee, Wisconsin, September circa 1940 (Reel 1)
    - Young Democrats Convention circa 1937 (Reel 1)
    - Lewiston, Maine, January 11, ? (Reel 1)
    - New Jersey, no date (Reel 1)
    - Untitled circa 1937 (Reel 1)
  - Speeches (Authorship uncertain)
    - Publicity Division-Mr. Murphy for Mrs-McAllister, 193 8 (Reel 1)
    - Social Security circa 1937 (Reel 1)
    - Defeat of "Unequal Rights" Amendment 1945-1946 i1944j (Reel 1)
  - Women's Division of the National Democratic Committee
    - Correspondence
      - General 1937 (Reel 1)
      - Upon resignation as director 1940 (Reel 1)
      - Molly Dewson 1937-1940 (Reel 2)
      - Frank Murphy 1937-1938 (Reel 2)
      - Eleanor Roosevelt 1938, 1940 (Reel 2)
      - Franklin D. Roosevelt 1938-1941 (Reel 2)
    - Democratic Digest Articles undated (Reel 2)
    - Equal Representation 1937-1938 (Reel 2)
    - Presidential Campaign 1940 (Reel 2)
    - Program messages 1937 (Reel 2)
    - Publicity 1938-1939 (Reel 2)
    - Report 1940 (Reel 2)
    - Report of the Activities of the Women's Division, Democratic National Committee in the 1940 Campaign, 1941 (Reel 2)
    - Reporter Plan
      - 1934-1936 (Reel 2)
      - 1937-1940 (Reel 2)
    - Speakers Bureau 1938 (Reel 2)
    - Speaking Tour, Coeur d'Alene, Missoula and Billings 1939 (Reel 2)
    - Statements and releases 1940 (Reel 2)
    - Washington State Conference 1939 (Reel 2)
    - Women in Politics 1938 (Reel 2)
  - Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform
    - Correspondence 1932-1935 (Reel 2)
    - Minutes and reports 1932-1935 (Reel 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1932-1935 (Reel 2)